嚇，田北辰嘅，我哋而家開始開會。
請阿梁國權先生同埋嘅陪同人士入會議室，唔該。
寫咗兩。
報議員，你係咪要發問嘅？
係。
首先就歡迎各位出席調查港深港高速鐵路香港段建造工程二五嘅背景及原委。
專責委員會嘅第八次公開言訊。
今日向專責委員會作證嘅係證人係香港鐵路有限公司行政總裁梁國權先生，梁生啊，再次多謝你再次嚟出席我哋呢個會議啊，就係協助我哋工作。
噉嘅專責委員會已經同意梁生嘅要求啦，可以有陪同人士出席言訊嘅。梁生嘅陪同人士咧，係金道律師事務所合夥人。
港鐵。
公司外聘法律顧問炳純先生，Mr. David Bateson。
噉就仲有就係港鐵公司首席法律顧問包偉明先生。
港鐵公司首席公司事務顧問黃美琪女士，同埋港鐵公司協調經理高速鐵路吳家華先生。
我哋想誒陪同人士注意就係上述誒，佢哋呢班陪同學生出席嘅人士咧，係唔可以向專責委員會發言。
本人提醒誒各位證人咧，就係本。
專責委員會係冇獲立法會授權行使《立法會權力及特權條例》第三百八十二章第九括弧一條嘅權力。
因此，證人係唔受第三百八十二章賦予證人嘅特權所保障。
喺詢問過程裏邊，根據第三百八十二章第十八條嘅規定。
對專責委員會提出嘅言訊主題上具關鍵性嘅問題，蓄意給予虛假嘅回答，或者向專責委員會提交虛假、失實、捏造或捏改嘅文件，而意圖欺騙專責委員會，即屬犯罪。
係，我相信證人會真誠咁協助委員會嘅工作。
專責委員會已經制定咗本身嘅工作方式同程序，本席請大家留意以下幾點。首先，第三百八十二章所定嘅議員特權，只係適用於言訊嘅過程。
所有議員，包括非專責委員會委員嘅議員，都應該避免喺言訊過程以外場合發表與言訊有關嘅意見。
另外，我想借呢個機會提醒旁聽。
誒今日言訊嘅公眾人士係唔受呢個誒同埋傳媒咧喺言訊過程以外場合披露言訊裏邊提供嘅證據咧係唔受第八十二章所保護。而所以，如果有需要嘅話，各位人士同埋傳媒朋友咧，應該就佢哋嘅法律責任咧。
徵詢法律意見。
喺守候嘅過程裏邊，本席會要求證人就佢曾經向專責委員會提交嘅文件作出確認。
啊！將文件納入為呢個專責委員會嘅證據。
另外，專責委員會已經決定，所有經專責委員會考慮並同意可以公開嘅文件，會上載喺立法會網頁供公眾查閲。
而家夠鐘，亦都係有足夠嘅發電人數，我宣佈言訊正式開始。
阿梁國權先生。
廣鐵公司曾於二零一五年八月十四日向專責委員會秘書提供一份文件，即係專責委員會文件第MTR四號。你而家係咪正式向專責委員會出示該份文件為證據？係。
梁生喺呢個。
誒，我聽秘書講，你係要求喺言開始之前誒，著會有一個開場嘅發言，係咪啊？係係噉啊！請你開始啦。唔該，多謝主席。
主席，各位委員，上次向各位交代之後啊，知道委員仲有事情想了解。
我會盡力回答大家嘅提問，不過唔好意思，大家都知道我中文唔係咁好。
為咗可以準確表達我嘅意思啊，好似上次一樣，我繼續用英文回答。
誒，梁生，呢個係你嘅權利。咁其實你中文都講得好好嘅。
多謝主席。噉我想問一問，就係你而家係咪係？但係你唔介意我係用翻中文，因為呢個係一向我都用開中文。唔介意，主席。阿主席，我啊啊，仲有少少英文，可唔可以講一講？啊，當然可以。啊，Honourable Chairman and Committee Members，thank you for giving me the opportunity to provide
information to the select committee on the express rail link project.
我會 start off with an update on progress of the project.
subsequent to the select committee hearing on 15th of July, we have provided supplementary information requested by the select committee to the best of our ability.
to address members' concerns, the supplementary information covers a wide range of issues, including project management and monitoring, as well as details of the delay recovery measures.
With the continuous efforts of our projects team, I am pleased to report to members that as of today, the overall completion progress of the Express Rail Link project is 74%.
We have made significant progress in a number of key areas. The 25 kilometre twin track underground tunnels are over 99% bored through, with only approximately 100 metres left to go. It is expected that full tunnel breakthrough.
會被達成，before the end of the year.
The structural works for all 14 buildings in Sackgon Stabling Siding and Emergency Rescue Siding have been completed, and the architectural builders' works are progressing steadily.
progress has also been made at the West Kowloon terminus by adopting blasting in parallel with mechanical methods. The overall excavation of the terminus is 95% complete, while 63% of the concrete structure has been cast.
The pace of steelwork fabrication and erection has also been improving.
for the rooftop structures, fabrication of all temporary steel has been completed, while fabrication of the permanent steel is 61% complete. The on-site erection of both is now well underway.
The electrical and mechanical, or E and M works, are also making good progress, with overall completion at 50%.
About 75% of the track areas are available for overhead line installation and track laying, with half the tracks now laid. At West Caledonian Terminus, E and M contractors now have access to about 95,000 square metres of workspace and building services.
installation has commenced in the platform areas on level B4.
As you are aware, the Express Rail Link is a large, complex and challenging project. It is the world's first all-underground high-speed railway project, which includes a fully underground terminus in the heart of the city at West Kowloon.
The West Kowloon terminus site occupies 11 hectares of reclaimed land. It is bounded by Kowloon Station to the west, Austin Station to the east, and the West Kowloon Cultural District to the south. The terminus is the largest de-excavation undertaking ever carried out in Hong Kong. The
presence of operating railway lines, high-rise buildings and busy main roads nearby adds to the complexity of the engineering challenges.
The project also involves 25 kilometres of twin-track underground tunnels connecting West Kowloon terminus with the boundary between Hong Kong and San Juan. The degree of engineering difficulty is significant.
as previously reported, the key causes of the delay in the construction of the express rail link include tunnel boring machine issues, the fast tracked front end of the project and late site possessions. Furthermore, unfavourable ground conditions such as higher than expected rock head levels, weak seams and the
presence of cobbles and boulders have also been a significant cause of delay.
at the same time, overall labour shortage of about 20% has significantly impacted the five railway projects which were being constructed concurrently, including the Express Rail Link.
自 commencement of construction, work sites have experienced difficulties in filling vacancies across all skill sets.
As mentioned in the second report by the independent board committee, a shortage of workers and supervisors has posed significant challenges to the construction programme of the express rail link.
Despite these challenges, we have taken our role and responsibility as the project manager very seriously. The corporation has all along acted in accordance with the entrustment agreements, which require us to oversee the design, construction and commissioning of the project. To this end, we have used our best endeavours to bring the project forward.
and at the same time provide regular updates and progress reports to the government, as well as to the Legislative Subcommittee on Matters Relating to Railways.
While there are still challenges in the remaining construction works, as the project manager, we continue to use our best endeavours to deliver the project according to the revised timetable. We have submitted the latest estimate of the cost to complete and programme to complete to government at the end of June. Government has since requested a.
Additional information, which we have provided accordingly.
please be assured that the corporation and government share the same objective of delivering the project as quickly as possible in the most cost-effective manner.
although the project may not have progressed as originally planned, more than 7,000 women and men are working hard day and night to push it forward. The MTR Corporation remains fully focused on the important task of delivering a world-class high-speed rail to support Hong Kong's continued development.
主席，多謝梁生。而家係咪正式？
向專責委員會出示你嘅開場發言稿作為證據。Yes, chairman.
我提醒各位委員，根據專責委員會工作方式同程序第十五段喺公開言訊裏邊，委員只係為確立同專責委員會嘅調查相關並屬於調查範圍內嘅事實。
議題問。
委員唔應該喺個言訊裏邊發表意見，或者係作出陳述。我會根據工作方式同埋程序第十六E段，決定某啲問題同埋某項證據係咪同專責委員會嘅職權範圍所在嘅調查相關，並屬於調查範圍內。
而根據工作方式同程序第十六F段咧，就委員係可以簡短咁作呢個跟進嘅問題。
同埋圍繞原來問題追問更詳細嘅答案。
或者係要求澄清所給予嘅答案。
而我作為主席，有酌情權決定某條問題係咪屬於跟進問題，以及應否容許委員提問。
該問題。
另外。
每位委員嘅提問時限係十分鐘，包括證人回應。
委員係可以選擇向一位或出兩位證人提問，但係。
就係好明顯，我哋只係得一位證人啊出席今次嘅言訊啦。
咁而家言訊咧就正式開始，誒為咗善用呢個言訊嘅時間咧，請委員嘅提問咧係盡量精簡同埋具體。
啊，同埋證人咧應該係明確同埋係到題嘅一個啊切實嘅回應嚇，好嘛？就唔好大家唔好浪費時間。
咁而家開始提問，連問連答十分鐘。
盧偉國議員。
誒，多謝主席。
誒主席，我誒有好幾個問題嘅，噉我第一個問題咧，我就想係就誒高鐵香港段工程嘅早期嘅估算嘅費用。
作出提問。
主席，我就想誒，透過你問阿梁生咧，就係。
根據廣深港高速鐵路香港段嘅獨立專家小組報告。
誒裡面嘅資料提及咧，就話港鐵公司喺二零零九年四月八號就高鐵香港段工程項目嘅委託費用嘅估算咧。
係九百五十億元。
但係咧，就喺二零一零年一月十六號咧，就呢個工程嘅項目嘅委託費用估算咧，係修定為六百五十億元㗎。咁呢個差距都相當大。
嗯，所以主席，我就就想嗯睇下咧，係誒係咪可以喺今日嘅會議上咧，誒梁生能夠解釋一下咧，就點解會喺都比較短嘅時間嚇，二零零九年四月八號去到二零一年一月十六號呢段期間咧就。
嗰個估算會有咁大幅度嘅減少啊，減少三百億元。
噉就誒，是否因為呢個第二份嘅委託協議書咧，就裏邊關於嗰個風險嘅釐定嘅問題，誒，港鐵公司係夠膽即係喺個股算上咧，能夠咁進取嚇一個誒咁咁嚇畀。
誒第一次嘅估算咧有咁大嘅差距，抑或係有其他嘅原因咧？係我想答咗呢個問題先。係我想問一問誒羅偉國議員，就係你講嗰個誒估算嗰個做工程造價同嗰個誒？
風險評，個評估風險評估，係個疑問係有啲誒係有關係嘅。嗱呢個我想，嗱我想問咧，當然誒阿梁生佢可以即係就佢誒自己嘅所知咧，就即係解釋嗰個差距。不過我其中一個誒，我我想即係睇嘅方向咧，呢。
個其實噉樣去定定咧，會唔會係好進取？呢個進取力都同呢個項目嗰個誒誒，大家合作個方式咧，個風險承擔方面有個關係。係啊，因為呢個咧其實誒啊，或者我不如我問問埋第個問題，就關風險嘅問題。係就係話誒，梁生作為。
呢個港鐵公司嘅前財務總監咧，其實有冇分析過港鐵公司咧喺而家呢個誒高鐵香港電嘅項目，以呢個服務經營權模式誒建造嘅，就誒由港鐵。
公司嘅管理、鐵路嘅建造，政府支付建造嘅管理費用咧，呢一方面咧，嗰個即係嗰個誒風險嘅狀況咧，誒呢個新嘅法嘅合作啦啊嘅模式咧，嗰個風險方面咧，其實佢當時有冇咩估估算咧？係梁生，或者嘗試作答啦。啊啊！
多謝 honourable member for that question.
Firstly, on the cost estimate, as members are aware, there were many experts involved at the initial stages in two thousand and eight and two thousand and nine and two thousand and ten in advising on different aspects of cost. Experts that were appointed by government and ourselves. The migration of the cost.
Estimates are well highlighted in the IEP report. In fact, it's on page sixty one of their report. As the honourable member mentioned back in April of two thousand and nine, there was a very initial estimate that was close to ninety five billion Hong Kong dollars. However, as well also highlighted.
在IEP報告，從4月到9月2009，有減少項目範圍，因為各位都知道，減少項目範圍也會帶來成本減少，成本預估。這些減少項目範圍，這點在第62頁政府報告中已經強調過。
Its IEP report includes a reduction in the number of tunnel boring machines from six to nine. It includes the deletion of platform screen doors. It includes a change of the vent building to an emergency access point. These reductions in scope allow for a.
減少那成本預測down to 73.9 billion dollars， as highlighted in the IEP report. At the same time， government have their own independent assessment of costs. They had their Jacobs， as I understand， being their adviser on the。
their visor on the cost to complete.
What I would further like to highlight, and this is well highlighted in the IEP report as well, is that subsequent to the tendering of all contracts, subsequent to the tendering of all contracts, in fact the contracts came in at a much lower amount than the.
Original estimate. So as highlighted on paragraph 331, indeed the of the 49 contracts that were investigated and reviewed by the IEP, those 49 contracts.
came in at an amount of 13.7 billion below the original estimates that were done back in 2009 and early 2010. Thank you, Chairman.
我哋過二誒主席就誒，似乎梁生就喺個答案中咧，就誒似乎亦都冇提到，因為個風險嗰個承擔方面咧有乜嘢嘅唔同咧，所以使到嗰個誒股選咧係咁進取。噉啊，梁生亦都講咗咧，就係話誒實際。
常翻嚟嘅投標個價錢咧，亦都都都真係切合佢哋嘅，即係調整咗，即係較低咗嘅嘅估算啦。不過咧，都減少咗工程範圍。另外一方面咧，就係話嗰個內容方面都有所唔同。誒，我進一步想提問咧，就係如果睇翻，假如嗰陣時個估算咧。
係因為個內容方面都有所調整，所以個比較客觀嘅估算。而實際上投標翻嚟個價錢咧，似乎誒梁生嘅誒頭先嘅顯示咧，即係話似乎啲印證咗嗰個估算唔係話即係有有咩好大嘅落差嘅。但係到今天就嗰個誒真係超支。
情況亦都咁嚴重咧，係是否即係顯示到咧？就喺嗰個誒項目管理嗰方面咧，特別嗰個成本方面咧，係即係出咗乜嘢嘅問題，引致到到今天我哋又睇到咁大嘅嘅升幅咧噉。盧偉國議員誒，我相信。
係今日個超支嘅問題咧，就唔係我哋嗰個委員會誒要調查嘅範圍之內。如果你係講個超支係因為由於由於嗰個舊年四月嗰個而而產生嗰啲超支咧，就你可以作出提問。但係之後嗰啲關於累積嗰啲噉嘅。
超支到今日為止咧，我哋係唔屬於我哋嘅調查範疇嚇。噉啊，不如我用誒另一個方式問咧，就係具體一啲啦。喺誒目前香港段嘅四十幾份嘅合約裏邊咧，就嗰個有幾多係未能夠如期開工嚇？一講如期開工。
咁如果未能夠如期開工咧，就可能就係話嗰個完工日期咧，亦都需要即係相應係有所調整。咁呢個亦都會唔會成為即係多份合約嘅滯後嘅原因咧？咁？
梁生。
啊。
Honourable member, thank you for that question. Firstly, as members are aware, the Express Rail Link is a very large and very complex project, as we have highlighted before. Difficulties encountered during construction would be inevitable for a project of this nature. And of course, when the project team comes across
這些困難，他們盡力克服延誤。有許多接口在列車連接中，有些接口在IEP和IPC報告中被強調。這些接口可能導致某些合同被。
perhaps slightly later tendered out than originally estimated, but the team, as always in the professional manner, would use their utmost to catch up the original schedule by using delay recovery measures and other measures.
主席，我想誒進一步誒問咧，就係誒亦都到即係牽涉到嗰個鹽嘅問題啦，嗯。
我相信都要睇咧，就係話嗰個風險管理嗰方面咧，即是否做得足夠。
咁喺呢度咧，亦都誒往往都係有兩種嘅風險管理嘅模式啦。一個所謂定升嘅風險嘅管理嘅模式，一個咧就係定量嘅風險管理嘅模式。咁喺呢一方面咧，就誒根據港鐵公司提供嘅文件都。
係話咧，係港鐵公司過往係採用定性嘅模式，包括誒香港誒呢個誒高鐵香港段嘅都係用呢個誒定性模式進行施工嘅管理，就係嗰個風險管理嘅。咁喺呢度咧，會唔會啊，梁生會唔會再檢視翻咧？其實喺定
定性同埋定量嘅風險模式管理之間咧，呢個選擇即是否合當咧？如果睇翻轉頭咧，會唔會用一啲定量嘅方式咧，又會對於嗰個風險方面、對呢個業務方面嘅管理咧，會有所幫助咧？
No, thank you, honourable member for that question. The honourable member is absolutely correct to say that generally there are two ways of assessing risk. One is a qualitative, and the other is a quantitative. In terms of looking at schedule risk, timetable risk, MTR has historically used
質的質的approach。This approach is in line with our project management systems. Now, this project management system is a system that was reviewed by a number of experts back in two thousand and eight and two thousand and nine. And in fact, those experts, both employed by government and M.
ECR have noted the robustness and the good control and the excellence of those of the project management system, which uses a qualitative a qualitative assessment for programme. I would also add, as highlighted in my written response to.
Similar question from the last select committee meeting. That from a cost to complete perspective, we do use a quantitative approach. So we have historically used a qualitative approach in line with our project management systems for schedule for timetable and a quantitative.
approach for costs.
都係個人係誒，對於呢個項目嘅管理咧，另一方面咧係相當重要咧，就係話喺個高層嘅工程管理方面嗰個人力。
嘅是否足夠嘅問題，咁因為同一時間咧，除咗高鐵嘅香港段咧，都有喺好幾個咧大型嘅鐵路項目進行之緊緊嘅，咁喺誒港鐵公司咧，係負責呢五個興建中嘅鐵路項目咧，就係一個嘅工程總監。
嗯。
啊，咁人即係具體邊位即係有變動啦。咁但係實際上都係以一個工程總監咧，係負責呢幾個誒同時進行緊嘅鐵路項目。誒，其實呢個噉樣會唔會嗰個工作量會太重咧？就係其實睇翻轉頭咧，會唔會誒有？
其他嘅即係管理上嘅安排，會使到高鐵香港段個進度咧，誒嗰個監督上誒風險管理上咧，都做得會更加係細緻，同埋係避免咗誒太多嘅疑問咧。咁阿梁啊，當時有冇足夠嘅專業？
支援係喺呢個工程方面啦。No, I thank you for that question. The
MTR， we have a very professional project management team. In fact, today that team has around 3,000 colleagues.
Each of the projects that we are undertaking is under a separate, is controlled and managed by a separate team. So there is a separate project manager for each of the new rail projects, including the Express Rail Link. Those project managers, of course, report.
to the project director, I truly believe that we have not just a very professional, highly qualified project management team in our projects division, but they are industrious. They seek solutions to issues when they arise, and it is a very
Very professional team. Thank you. Yes, I think the question嗰個問題咧係。
Are they were they adequate?
啊！
In assessing the project management systems, I think the IBC also looked at this matter and they commented that the project management team is of a highly professional and have done their best to catch up with schedule delays whenever those issues.
arose係答唔答到你問題？誒答到啊，主席，我想問都喺呢環節，我想問最後一個，因為頭先我問咧都係由呢個誒港鐵公司嗰個管理層方面睇誒呢個誒風險管理啊項目嘅進度啊同埋疑問嘅問題誒，從另一個層面咧就係承建商嗰方面啦。
噉係就係梁生嘅經驗咧，就係你覺得我哋而家誒負責高鐵項目嘅嘅承辦商咧啊，同埋承承建商咧，佢哋。
是否真係誒能夠好配合咧去推動呢個高鐵項目？而另一方面咧，就喺管理上咧，係對於呢一方面嘅誒監督與推行咧，港鐵公司又是否做得足夠咧？咁？
No, no. Thank you for that question. We share the same objective as the contractors. The contractors have the same objective to complete the project, complete this project as quickly as possible. There is, as highlighted in the IPC report, very good and significant project management over these.
contractors， so the contractors and ourselves have and share the same objective.
好，主席喺呢個環節，我暫時提問到呢度，唔該。好，阿譯志明議員。哇，唔該，主席喺呢度啊，先多謝阿梁生今日再次出席我哋呢個言訊。誒，第一個問題咧就係嗱，我哋睇翻咧港鐵公司嘅獨立董事委員會嘅第一份報告裏邊咧就講。
項目團隊對路政署係保留咗一啲關鍵嘅項目進度嘅信息。
而路政署嘅鐵路擴展處嘅處長陳志恩先生。
喺佢嘅陳述書裏邊咧就有講到嘅，佢話儘管路政署係記按呢個既定嘅匯報機制向港鐵公司要求提供資料，但係喺有啲情況之下咧，路政署係唔能夠適時地獲得呢啲嘅資料。嗱，噉我嘅問題咧有下列五個，第一。
個係對於獨立委員會嗰個嘅第一份報告嘅相關內容，同埋路政署阿陳先生指出港鐵有關嘅問題，我想聽一聽阿梁先生你對呢啲嘅講法嘅一啲回應。呢個第一。
第二咧，呢啲有關問題點解會發生咧？
當中係咪有港鐵嘅人員係做得唔妥當，甚至乎係有過失咧？
第三就係就呢個獨立委呢個董事委員會嘅第一份報告所指，項目團隊對路政署係保留咗一啲關鍵項目進度嘅信息。你可唔可以向我哋交代一下，當中係涉及一啲乜嘢嘅關鍵項目，同埋有啲咩信息咧？
第四咧就係，你會唔會認為港鐵公司係未有適當同埋適時地向路政署提供項目嘅相關資料？
係因為港鐵內部其實已經認為進度係無法追回，但又唔想咁快公開，咁咧就故咧，而咧係採取呢個下策。
咁如果港鐵係冇出現呢啲問題嘅話，咁又為何有所隱瞞咧？
第五個最後一個問題就係喺高鐵項目嘅疑問問題上邊，你會唔會認同港鐵公司同政府之間嘅溝通同合作係足夠嘅？而目而嗰個目前嘅疑問係同政府無關。
唔該，主席，梁生五條問題。嗱，介紹啊，Thank you, honourable member. Firstly, I would say I would start by saying that there was full disclosure of all information to government, the Rail Development Office and other departments. This is well highlighted, I believe, both in the IPC.
and the IEP report, and I also believe that when Mr Kekilau and Mr Henry Chang were giving evidence, they also said that whenever our Development Office asked for information or documents from MTR, MTR would provide the information or documents to them.
啊！
This full disclosure is, I believe, well communicated or well highlighted in the reports by the independent board committee of MTR as well as the independent expert panel IEP from government. I think the IBC report goes on in the same report that.
The honourable member mentioned to say that government RDO and MTR worked in a collaborative and cooperative manner.
我理解， and as highlighted in the first IBC report, the information which Mr. KK Lau and Mr. Henry Chang was referring to may be information relating to events in November of 2013.
not forgetting in at that period our projects director, our projects team was still trying to get further information from the contractor of one key project. This is contract number eight hundred and ten A to understand in full the timetable for their activities.
Without having that understanding and that information from the contractor, it is very difficult to it is it would be inappropriate to speculate at that time. So I believe that the project's team at that time was really waiting for the final timetable from the 810A contractor, which was only.
available in early 2014. So, in summary, Chairman, my view is that there was, and this is supported by the IBC and the IEP report, disclosure was in accordance with the entrustment agreement, the disclosure was in a timely manner, and there was adequate.
Disclosure.
啊！主席，我聽咗阿梁生嘅講法，噉你就歸咎咗喺一個特別嘅項目，因為未有一個充足評估啦。咁所以咧，你哋就啊未鋪咗一啲嘅information。但係如果你哋話畀我聽咧，你同政府合作無間咧，我又唔覺得呢啲問題點解唔可以攤出嚟，大家講清楚喎。
嚇，免咗個誤會，因為而家有兩個accusation係指住話你哋冇提供足夠資料嘛，係有蓄意隱瞞嘅感覺喎。
No, thank you, honourable member. Firstly, I would say that at no time was there any any intent or any thinking of hiding or withholding any information from any parties. There was significant disclosure of information, as well as many many meetings between.
Government representatives of government, MTR, as well as the so-called M and V consultant Jacobs, as members are aware, Jacobs had undertaken over 250 audits in that period. So there was constant exchange of information as well as disclosure, as I mentioned, as highlighted in the IP.
ABC report， there was a collaborative and cooperative man manner was taken in the discussions between government and MTR to resolve the problems that were coming up in the project. So this was working together to resolve the problems.
Coming up, we take our responsibility very seriously under the entrustment agreement, and we have acted, I believe, in accordance with our obligations under the entrustment agreement. Once again, the the matter which honourable member mentioned relating to November two thousand and thirteen was at
時間當我們還在，或MTR，如在IBC報告中所指出，還在等待一個時間表，從810A承包商來看，這個所謂的最低運營方法是否可行。
Thank you, chairman。啊，主席，我就聽到梁生就即係覺得佢哋係冇蓄意隱瞞啦嚇，即係佢答我第一組嘅問題。嗱，噉我第二個問題咧，其實都同呢個嘅疑慮係有啲相關嘅。
誒有批評就話咧，誒呢個係一個好複雜嘅項目，我哋知道嘅，但係咧就冇一個所謂嘅integrated嘅master plan。
咁咧就呢個項目咧分拆四廿幾個合約嚇，有開工期，有個別嘅完工期。
但係咧，就因為有啲延而導致到有啲項目咧，後續個項目咧係延遲開工，但係又冇去修定嗰個嘅完工期。
咁咧又由於政府咧或者係監管嘅部分咧，又冇一個所謂嘅master plan，佢又睇唔到你嗰個所謂誒critical path影響到咩程度咧噉。
咁呢個喺項目管理嚟講，已經係一個問題本身已經存在啦嚇。咁但係我哋聽到有啲講法咧，上誒上一次嘅嘅聆訊咧嘅嘅言訊咧。
就話其實咧，港鐵公司內部係有一個嘅啊，呢個所謂master plan嘅。不過咧就冇搦嚟同政府分享啫啊，即係我聽到係噉樣啦。如果我係聽錯嘅，主席你可以誒改修正我嚇。我想問啦，即係咁點解咧？既然你有，點解又唔同政府相關嘅監管部門分享？
大家可以溝通得更好，係咪蓄意隱瞞咧？又係。
梁生，Thank you, honourable member, for that question. Firstly, as the honourable member had mentioned, there is such an integrated master plan, and that integrated master plan is updated on a periodic basis, and also updated using the so-called P six Primavera software format. This is in
In accordance with the MTR project management approach.
the reporting on the member's question on reporting to government there was as I mentioned and continues to be very regular reporting to government. In fact, the monthly reports or the reports going to government, many of them stretch over two hundred pages. There was a lot of information in those.
報告。
啊！我想問一問就係你話個integrated嘅master plan咧。嗱，當然你一個咁大工程咧，你會涉及好多唔同嘅範疇啦。嚇，噉你係係咪即係一百樣嘅嘢，全部都係integrated嘅有個master plan喺度啊？就如果有嘅話咧，呢個master呢個integrated。
Integrated嘅master plan係咪淨係地鐵、港鐵公司知道啊？政府知唔知道呢個integrated嘅master plan嘅咧？啊，Chairman，firstly to confirm there is this integrated master programme， and in in fact in addition to the integrated master programme， we have the sync or track。
Related installation programme, which also supplements the integrated master programme to look at, amongst other things, the installation of electrical and mechanical systems. Once or at the time the civil works are completed. Once again, as I mentioned, there was regular reporting to.
政府，那包括過200頁的報告，on合同，as well as on cost and other aspects。Those reports were very much on a very regular basis.我我唔係講reporting嘅問題。如果你係有個噉嘅plan，係一個非
食嘅嘢係存在嘅。
咁嗰個政府係咪有呢嚿嘢咧？呢個integrated master program咧，係政府喺全國係畀咗政府嘅咧。
主席，我。
not in an I I'm not in a position to answer that question. I will have to revert to you on that. What we're very clear of is the reporting on the regular basis that has been given to government. These two hundred plus page reports, which looks at and talks about the overall programme as well as individual contracts as well as the cost aspects.
我諗你check清咗之後，你翻嚟話翻畀我聽，因為點解咧？reporting還reporting，你個你嗰個誒，你個計劃咧，呢個整個協呢個係共融呢個計計劃嘅話咧，呢個計劃係政府係有冇嘅。你係咪全盤已經畀咗政府嘅？即係我唔講你reporting嗰句，reporting嗰句係做咗之後，你係根據嗰個。
你個plan嚟去去向政府報告啦。咁但係嗰個報告嗰個計劃咧，就政府本身有冇攞住喺手嗰度嚟睇呢個報告咧？呢個係亦都係好重要。我想你翻翻嚟話翻畀我聽，好嘛？出完之後，I can I revert，Chairman啊，唔該你啊，唔該主席，我仲有一個問題想問嘅。誒喺啊梁生。
你今日嘅發言稿裏邊嘅第九段咧，嗱，其實你第一次嚟嗰個言訊咧，你個個嘅誒文件咧都有嘅強調咧，就呢個勞工短缺所產生嘅問題。
誒，我喺度再次講咧，如果羅偉國議員都記得嘅咧，喺二零一三年十一月嗰個嘅事務委員會咧，我哋係質疑你哋有冇面對勞工短缺嘅問題嘅啊，因為呢個好可能係你言嘅其中一個主要因素。
但係當時你哋出席嘅同事咧，就再次強調咧，你哋唔受呢個勞工短缺嘅影響。我仲好記得黃國興議員咧，臨離開呢個會議室，當時嘅會議室咧，佢就話佢哋誒非常讚賞港鐵嚇，即係能夠喺咁困難嘅環境之下，能夠做到嚇，佢直頭封你哋做典範。
嗱，咁而家咧，我再一而再、再而三喺唔同嘅文件咧，睇到港鐵公司咧就開始咧就提出呢個勞工短缺對你哋嘅影響。
咁當時係咪有啲嘢想隱瞞咧？又係。
即係點解你唔肯當值就承認？即係你係受影響咧。
Thank you, honourable member, for that question. I was not at the particular meetings that the honourable member mentioned. However, the shortage of labour is a situation as highlighted by a number of parties that pertains across the whole construction industry. In fact.
I think in the IEP report there was a comment with regards to the labour situation, and that comment is that even back in July 2013, July 2013, the president of the Hong Kong Construction Association has identified in.
從survey of his organisation， that a vacancy rate, a shortage rate of fifteen percent is prevalent across the industry, which was equates at that time to ten thousand workers. So I would say that the shortage of labour is an issue that has impacted both the programme as.
Well, as importantly, the costs of the express rail link. Once again, there was never any. There's never any intent to withhold any information from from anyone. I think this labour shortage situation is well known in the.
We have, as a result of this labour shortage situation, done quite a bit to try to encourage more workers to either join the industry or to workers to come back into the industry. These include participation in job fairs. This includes working with relevant government.
Bureaus. This includes enhancing the enhancing the.
The on-site situation for our construction colleagues, which have aspects like life insurance being provided, health checks, etc. So we have done what we can to try to encourage more people to come in to the construction workforce.
啊！主席，我當然誒明白阿梁生講乜嘢啦。我哋梗係覺得當時誒勞工短缺問題對你可能產生影響。我之所以同盧偉國議員會再三提問呢樣嘢嘛。咁但係喺一三年嘅月嘅十一月，你哋都唔想誒mit嚇承認你哋受影響，係咪因為當時你嘅出席嘅不當然？
問你又唔啱嘅，因為唔係你出席個會議啦嚇。咁咧就係誒擔心議員會追問，咁會唔會因此有言誤啊？噉你其實想避咗個問題啊。咁但係咧就去到二零一四終於爆煲啊，即係點解唔早啲承認有呢個問題咧？咁多謝主席。係啦，梁生啊，no thank you again for that question. The
係。
I think we have actually been quite open about the shortage of labour and the impact of labour shortage on the our projects, including the Express Rail Link. In fact, I have in front of me. This is a letter from Transport and Housing Bureau to the Secretary General of the.
立法會顧問秘書處，22號1月2014，這必須係在參考22號11月2013，和在這在附表到那封信，它註明那，和我引述，而XRL項目需要約10,000個。
Construction workers and technical professional staff, contractors have so far employed around 8,500, and it gives a breakdown of the shortage of 1,500. So I think there has been regular and full disclosure of the challenges which.
We were facing in labour shortage. We have done, we do what we can to overcome those challenges, Chairman. And I mentioned some of the items that we have taken to try to overcome those challenges.
哦，唔該，excuse me。
好，下一位係。
恬不神怡。
即係。
啊！我主要咧就係跟進翻上一次我同阿梁生嘅對話，有一個十二分鐘，有一個五分鐘，但問嚟問去咧都問唔到咩嘢，因為啊，梁生係其實好叻嘅。
好識回答問題。
不過今次咧，我就真係要即係認真，誒搞清楚。
我上次咧係想知道喺零九年。
港鐵同政府達成協議，五年之內六百幾億可以起到。
呢條高鐵。
係咪太過樂觀？
咁當時咧，阿梁生就三番四次話計個數。
doable, doable.
咁跟住我就問。
當時你哋其實明知冚碳不足，既然你知道冚碳不足。
點可能啊？話樂觀到五年起條六百幾億嘅鐵路可以誒doable咧？咁？
咁當時咧。
梁生嘅答案咧，就係話。
There was a lot of work done, and that work was also aided by a number of professional third parties in coming up with that programme.
There was an agreement and based on the work done, there was an assessment done, which was the schedule, the original programme, blah blah blah blah blah. Okay.
好啦。
喺你嘅第四十六段嘅。
陳述書嗰度咧，你都有話嘅。
誒喺西九龍總站嘅工地勘測咧，平均就每十四點四米咧就有個即係鑽孔啦。
咁呢個係符合啲標準嘅。
但係咧。
我所問嘅咧？
就係喺。
二零零九年，你同政府同意呢個。
時間表同埋呢筆，即係。
誒建築費。
一零年嚟立法會攞錢嘅時候咧。
其實咧。
成條佐敦道。
同埋成個高爾夫球會咧。
係完全冇恨嘆過。
我嘅記錄咧，你高爾夫球會去實施呢個十四點四米嘅陷潭咧，係二零一零年嘅三月。
咁嗰陣時咧，就已經過咗立法會攞到錢啦。
咁個問題係點解廣鐵可以叻到啊？
喺。
未勘探之前啊！
都可以知道勘探嘅結果咧。
而事實上咧，佐敦道由頭到尾都冇做過氹氹。
因為封路好麻煩。
而結果，我哋今日所知咧。
就係因為個護土牆要起喺佐敦道下邊，先至可以去挖掘嗰啲花崗巖。
而嗰個護土牆就遲咗一年嘅。
噉你當時係完全喺二零零九一零年嘅年初咧，係冇做過呢兩方面嘅談。
但係竟然咧就話咧誒呢啲嘢做到足，呢啲嘢做到足係攞完錢之後事後發生嘅事。我而家問係當時同政府嗰個誒協議。
係二零一五年通車，六百六啊幾七啊億嗰陣時，你係完全冇呢啲資料嘅。
但係梁總裁，你都三番四次話There was a lot of work done，但呢啲work done was after。
The.
the the agreement between you and government on the time frame and the expenses呢係用中文，一係用英文，如果咪就變咗好難好難記載嘅。你要你啲法。
誒，咁誒，你想我用一句語言係嘛？因為我諗住如果係雙語咧，我容易啲表達，不過。
冇問題啦，我諗啊梁總在聽到盡量啦，好唔好啊？好啊，好啊。
係，阿梁總裁。
即係我始終要搞清楚呢件事啊。No, thank you, honourable member for that question. As the honourable member mentioned, there was a lot of work done before the signing of the entrustment agreement, and there were a number of experts and third party involved, both from government as well as from us.
There was significant site investigation done prior to signing the SoCo EA2. As the honourable member mentioned, however, at Jordan Road we cannot do site investigation there because of the volume of traffic, and it was inappropriate to close the road to do site investigation on the golf.
Driving range, the golf driving range in West Kowloon, as the honourable member mentioned, there was site investigation done after after we took possession of the site. The with
Large complicated projects like the express rail link, there is.
A lot of work that needs to be done in the initial stages, and there is in the assessment of the cost to complete a contingency. The there are matters which
Would always impact the project. That would not be known at the beginning of the project. The contingency is there to take care and address those issues. I would highlight once again that after the tender contracts came back, and this is well highlighted in the IEP report, because of the lower.
tender prices, the contingency, the amount of contingency actually increased very significantly. So it is with the use of the contingency allows for unknown factors which may not have been known at the time of entering into the project agreement. I would further add in terms of the granite that.
The presence of the granite is known. It is just the formation of that granite that was perhaps less certain. And the issue was that the granite can be removed. It is a question of time to remove it.
主席，呢個就係正正嘅問題啦。即係聽阿梁生講咧，就話佢明知道當時係勘探不足。
啊！去到個程度咧，成條佐敦道即係嗰個成個護土牆啊！
嗰個位置啊，完全冇做咁淡。
同埋咧，成個高爾夫球練習場咧冇做過，我諗大家都知道個場幾大㗎啦，就正正今日西九總站佔咗大部分。
一個咁關鍵性嘅弧道場嘅位置，同成個高爾夫球場喺一零年嚟立法會攞錢冇做過冚攤噉啊。梁生咧就話：錢咧佢係預得松嘅，佢認為如果真係有意想不到嘅嘢咧，佢都用錢可以搭救。
噉，但係時間咧，梁生。
時間唔係錢買得到㗎。
咁時間點咧？
首先，Tim，perhaps I could just comment on the site investigation. There was significant site investigation done, and as I had mentioned last time, the site investigation was in line with government guidelines and in fact of a higher standard.但梁生唔好意思，你而家重複緊。
你之前已經承認最緊要嗰兩個陷探係一零年三月之後先做嘅，而佐敦道根本從來都冇做過。你只不過正話答咧就係錢嗰度咧，你預得好松啊，認為就算真係誒有意想不到嘅嘢咧，你都可以補到。但係我而家問係問時間，啲時間買唔？
翻嚟㗎嘛？你五年啊，點可能預啊？下邊嗰八萬五立方米嘅花崗巖啊，全部係左端到下低，而你挖得咁辛苦咧，係咪？咁嗰陣時你係咪真係太樂觀啊？
Chairman, so with the the adequate site investigations that were done for the project, with regards to the timetable, as members are aware and well highlighted in the IEP report, there were a number of third parties that reviewed and looked at the timetable, the programme to complete.
Together with MTR, and all along the
而家講緊係一零年嚟立法會攞錢兩三，唔係講緊幾年後喎。嗰陣時你憑咩嘢認為啊？一個咁大嘅範圍冇勘探，你竟然可以拍心口話五年。
交貨啊！
你承唔承認當時非常之粗疏？唔係你，唔係你本人。
OK，成個港鐵高層、主席、董事局非常之粗疏。係劉生，Thank you, honourable member for that question. Once again, I it is my view, and from all the reports that we have seen, that adequate, adequate site investigation had been done。你點可以講呢句？
或者你啱啱先承認一零年一月嚟立法會攞錢，正話嗰兩個地方乜嘢陷探都冇，點可以？你而家話你覺得係adequate咧？係啊，或者畀個機會阿梁生答答佢意思就係你未作出呢個咁重要嘅位置，你冇作出嘅陷探，點可以同即係承諾話？
五年內可以係完成呢個工程。
No, I thank you for that question, Chairman. The
Not forgetting that the site investigation, and I apologise, apologise if I'm repeating myself here. If the site investigation was of a standard that met government guidelines and a higher standard than across the construction industry.
The West Kaloon Terminus is eleven hectares. The Jordan Road area is but one part of that, and I believe a relative.哥爾夫球場幾大？I do not have, chairman. The至少都幾個公頃啦。誒，嗱，即係畀畀個機會佢答答啦，好嘛？
主席啊，佢冇呢個資料，我就係想講一句嘢。唔係OK，佢冇資料，佢話主席，我就係想講一句嘢啫。好唔好？好，即係我覺得我係實事。呢個你comment嚟嘅係咪？係我comment啊！我係同你講嘅，主席，我覺得我係實事求是，將將當時嘅情況攞出嚟，但係我覺得。
我聽到嘅回應係完全係避而不答，避而不答，重複緊一樣唔合邏輯嘅嘢。
咁講真咧，我其實真係幾失望。
其實佢直情認佢當時係冇睇到呢樣嘢，咁疏忽咗其實好簡單啫嘛。係，但係佢一路話當時咧有曬呢啲噉嘅資料，但係當時冇啊，係事後先有啫嘛。我個問題係當時佢憑咩承諾五年做到啊嘛？
啱啱咪，大家大家都得到佢嘅答案。佢答到中唔足夠，大家會做咧。我哋會做個評評，我哋做做個評估嘅答案中唔足夠啦，好嘛？OK，Chairman，I could also，梁生係畀個機會你再有有冇有補充係咪？係，先生，主席，請講。I would。
首先，Westcarrloan terminus is a very large, eleven hectares site. There were four hundred bore, six hundred boreholes drilled for site investigation on that site, spaced fourteen point four metres apart. I would also say that in the Jordan Road area, in the Jordan Road area, we have available.
existing data of the utilities situation under Jordan Road. So when the agreement was the second entrustment agreement was signed with government, we have existing data with regards to the utilities situation under Jordan Road as well as.
啲細 investigations we have done係咁高球場咧。
嗱，你講唔出有幾大啊？個十一公頃之中，高球場至少都有幾公頃話，係咪？啊，嗰個算唔算大咧？Chairman, thank you for that question. The the golf driving range is of course in two components. There is a driveway with a parking lot, and there is the driving range itself. As I understand it from the various reports.
ports， there was certain investigation done in the driveway and the parking lot. Although, of course, we were not able to close the driving range. 啊，好唔該。我聽，如果你再有問題，第二輪啊，田北辰議員，我想都想跟進一下關於呢個氫探問題。啲因為路政處嗰個誒陳志恩先生曾經。
指出咧，佢導致高鐵項目嘅延誤咧，有好多原因。其中一個咧，就係涉及呢個工程工地嘅勘測同埋呢個項目設計嘅。
噉就我想問一問就係誒喺呢個誒工地呢個勘察嘅方面咧，港鐵公司係投放咗有幾多資源啊？包括嘅人手同費用噉樣，你有冇一個粗略嘅一個估計咧，梁生？
啊。
主席，我唔係有嗰個信息，可能我會有啲資料，但係我唔係有嗰個資料。
範疇嘅估算咧同埋預算係出現較大較大嘅偏差，會唔會有噉嘅情況出現咧？梁生。
Chairman, my understanding, and this is also in the various reports by the IBC and the IEP, my understanding is that there was adequate site investigation done, which includes the depth of the various holes and the boreholes drilled. Those boreholes are drilled 14.4 metres apart.
There could be undulation of rocks or different core stones between those 14.4 metres. So there was significant site investigation done, which is in accordance with government's guidelines and even of a higher standard than used in the industry.
O.K.咁如果係冇呢個疏忽同埋不足嘅話，
噉就誒，咁當然係，你會對呢個不可預知同埋難以預測嘅因素情況咧，都會有個比較上誒好嘅掌握啦。應該就嚇。
噉係咪誒？噉你有冇因應呢啲噉嘅問題咧？係制定一啲緩衝期咧？係工程嘅。
咁如果係有嘅話，點解會仲要出現咁多噉嘅言？你明白我我個問題？我問題就係你係如果係有你有較為掌握一啲噉嘅不即係難以預測嘅情況嘅話咧，你都會對佢有一個基本嘅掌握。咁有冇？
你。
用啲誒手段咧，係作出一啲緩衝期，啲工程緩衝期，緩衝期，咁咧唔會導致有咁多疑問。
I think, chairman, as I mentioned, although the ground investigation done is in line with government guidelines and higher industry standards, with boreholes being fourteen four metres apart, there's unfortunately the unfortunately.
times when issues with rocks will be missed just because of the rock formation.
I think on the schedule, there was a lot of work done with regards to the original schedule and the programme to complete. And once again, with the information at hand, the experts were of the view that the programme to complete.
With the knowledge of the site conditions, was adequate, was doable but tight.
Alright. Okay.
何孟政議員。
Thank you, Mr. Leung. In your opening statement, you said the overall completion progress of the project is now, as of today, 74%.
I.E. just under three quarters.
of completion. Now, those figures hardly impressive.
I'd say, and you did mention towards the end of your statement that there are still challenges in the remaining construction works. I just wonder.
What may be the largest challenge remaining? Question one, that is. And my question number two is: you keep, well, we we kept we keep getting allegations, if not accusations, that
The MTRC had withheld information from the government, in particular the highways department, and you kept telling us previously that oh no no no, whatever information they needed, we would have disclosed.
但係，problem是，一，We don't know what we don't know。
I mean, one cannot ask questions when one doesn't know what to ask, right? So on this.
information disclosure business，would you say would you acknowledge that the MTRC had behaved somewhat improperly，if not dishonestly？
Question number two, and my.
第三個問題是，先前你也 acknowledge 了，當它來到風險管理。
你用質質的評估 for timetables and so on， measuring what you call robustness。
and then of course you use quantitative assessment for costs and things.
Would you now, with hindsight, acknowledge that there were so many incompatibilities between the two? Your overly optimistic approach in qualitative assessment has out
Ultimately led to your quantitative.
wrong assessments， right？
三個問題， for the time being， thank you.
兩三，嗯，嗱。
Thank you, honourable member, for the for those questions. Firstly, on the challenges which the project continues to face, as the honourable member rightly mentioned, the project is seventy four percent complete. The tunnel sections between the West Kowloon terminus and the border with
San Juan is now over ninety nine percent complete, dug through, excavated. We have only just around one hundred metres of tunnel left to go out of twenty five plus kilometre twin track twin bore tunnel. The challenges which the project will continue to face. Once again, the
shortage of labour, particularly in the so-called electrical mechanical, the E and M phase that the project is coming into, this will be a challenge, and of course we would have we will have our our measures to try to overcome those that particular challenge. Secondly, the erection and construction.
Of the so-called station entrance building, which incorporates the atrium and roof of the structure, that will also be a challenge for the project. And thirdly, the productivity rate in physically building the structure. I mentioned that there has been reasonable progress in.
在terms of the physical building of the structure, but that structure still needs to be completed. So those are some of the challenges going forward with regards to this particular project.
The second question on information. Once again.
There was significant information and amount of information provided to government. This is well highlighted in the independent expert panel, the IEP report as well as the IBC report. There were not just information provided. There was very regular meeting between government officials and ourselves.
on top of that, as highlighted in the IEP and the IPC report, government has the M and V consultant Jacobs, who were also looking at the whole project. And in fact, as I mentioned before, during this period, the M and V consultant had themselves.
undertakeن250 audits. Their findings were reported to government, and there would be follow-on and follow-up of such findings.
I think the third question, which really comes back to risk management, the qualitative and the quantitative assessment. The qualitative assessment is a methodology that has worked very well in the past. It has delivered a number of our previous rail projects. It is a part of
The project management systems which we have to follow under the entrustment agreements.
The project management systems, as members are aware, was reviewed prior to government and MTR entering into the second entrustment agreement. And in fact, the various reviews comes up with words such as robust, good control, best of breed, and internal.
和評估，那會suggest that it is of a very high standard. It is based on that that I understand government entered into the second entrustment agreement with the governance and processes that were also put into place. So the qualitative assessment is an assessment with
Which one has worked well in the past. Secondly, it's part of the processes that we have had and that we are supposed to follow. And thirdly, part of the process that has been reviewed prior to entering into the entrustment agreements and have been well commented on, and in fact has been have been.
by the experts involved.
主席，Mr. Chairman，can I understand that Mr. Leung has practically categorically denied any improper or dishonest conduct when it comes to information disclosure?
exactly what you're saying呢個係好或者你係咪咁即係噉嘅意思啊？梁生，Chairman，I I I would say that at no time was there any intent, any intent in on behalf on the part of MTR to hide or withhold any information. The information as requested was provided.
There was a collaborative, cooperative working environment between government departments and ourselves.
That is, those are well borne out in the IBC and the IEP report.
冇噉嘅意圖，黃邦政議員佢話。Right, ah, my very last question. Um, there's no point to ask Mr. Leung whether there's any negligence on the part of himself or the MTRC. Right, that is um, well, futile question. But again, with
hindsight， you did say the MTRC is he had behaved somewhat overly optimistic in the over the entirety of the project， something to that effect。
what could have done better?
或，how you could have done better， in any way， in what areas or on what fronts， speaking， as of today。
唔該，多謝你 for that question, honourable member, as
As I mentioned at the last meeting, the
過optimism of the the project team led to MTR reporting late, reporting late the delay. I do not the overoptimism did not lead to the delay. It was the overoptimism led to the late reporting of the delay. The delay, the causes of delay are well.
highlighted in the various reports, and I will not go into that again. With due respect, isn't that just a word game?
啊！
Remember the what MTR has done in answer to your question is from the reports of the independent board committee. There were a number of recommendations made by the independent board committee. MTR has followed those recommendations and implemented.
或的建議，那些建議，一次再，，好高亮在報告中，包括一，的設立一個資本工程委員會，資本工程委員會現在已經運作數個月，第二，它包括對報告機制的加強，那些加強包括使用所謂。
或交通燈， as well as the use of milestones. Those have all been incorporated in our processes.
我 rest，我 rest。
誒，下一位。
係誒範國威員，好啊，唔該，主席。誒，我想問啊，梁國強先生啊，關於你喺上一次嘅言訊裏邊咧，你就好清楚講咗，就話拒絕去承認港鐵咧喺高鐵工程超支延誤呢一件事上邊咧，係有任何嘅隱瞞嘅。你話？
冇隱瞞，更加咧就話呢個委託協議咧就冇施加呢個叫絕對的義務嚇，絕對嘅義務就要求港鐵喺二零一五年嘅八月之前要完成工程，同埋咧設定呢個工程費用嘅上限。
但係梁國權先生，你上次嘅言訊咧，你當其時答我問題咧，講得好清楚，冇越絕對義務呢個講法，而唔係委託協議書裏邊白紙黑字嘅條文噉樣係。即係換言之咧，換言之咧，呢個係你口講，呢個你嘅講法係你單方面嘅理解。
OK，咁所以我想問啦，就係既然港鐵認為委託協議裏邊嘅員工時間可以係修定，係冇梁先生、李閣下講嘅絕對義務係按時係去完成工作嘅。主席，我第一個問題就係話點解上一任嘅行政總裁偉達成先生？
會喺二零一三年嘅十一月同當期時運輸及房屋局嘅緊急會議上邊，就要求政府唔好向我哋立法會嘅鐵路事小組報告通車日期係有所延誤，同埋反對政府咧就將工程延誤原原本本噉。
樣咧係向公眾交代咧。
第二就係當其時，你哋嘅反對理據咧，就係因為港鐵要喺二零一五年，即係今年通車嘅死線嘅deadline，所以咧係可以向呢個誒承建商施壓去趕趕工嘅。咁港鐵點解係不惜係要提高呢個嘅成本，畀更加多嘅錢都要打？
至二零一五年嘅通車嘅目標咧，如果梁先生你講話冇呢個絕對義務，誒係要去完工嚇，要喺二零一五年嘅八月之前完工嚇，你其實係咪講緊或者係間接承認咗港鐵係有責任係去按時完工嘅咧？係主席呢個係。
我第一個問題係。
梁生，請你答。
Thank you, Chairman, for that question. I think first and foremost, MTR, we take our responsibility under the entrustment very, very seriously, and we take all steps to ensure that we meet our obligation under the entrustment agreement, as I mentioned last time. And I think it's well highlighted in the IEP report.
This is the independent expert panel report, which is commissioned by government. It is well highlighted in the factual annexure by Price Waterhouse Coopers, on the basis that the timetable to complete, as well as the cost to complete, are estimates in the entrustment agreement and subject to change.
In fact, the IEP report very clearly sets out what the mechanisms are to adjust the timetable in the interest time. Chairman, I will not read out the relevant paragraph. The member mentioned the meeting in November of two thousand and thirteen. I was not.
Personally, at that meeting, so I do not know what was said in that meeting. All I have is from our IBC report, which has interviewed all the a number of people who were present at that meeting. As I understand it, in that particular meeting in November two thousand and thirteen.
With the previous CEO, the comment from the IBC report or the comment in the IBC report was that the previous projects director and the previous CEO were of the view that to keep pressure on the contractors, to keep pressure on the contractors.
It is important to keep to that 2015 opening date. That is in accordance with the IBC report. Because I was not in that meeting, I really cannot comment otherwise on what they have said.
主席，個問題唔係你當其時喺唔喺個會議上邊，而係港鐵嘅行為係證明咗客觀上邊你哋係有責任按時係去完工嚇，你客觀上係證明咗呢樣嘢。主席，我第二個問題就係，或者等佢答咗先好啊。啊，第
As I mentioned under the entrustment agreement, this is well highlighted in the IEP report. MTR, we have to use our best endeavours, which we have under the entrustment agreement. The timetable and the cost to complete are estimates, which are subject to adjustments in accordance with that.
trust agreement係唔該，佢佢重複緊佢答案啦，已經係嚇主席。我第二個問題就係十月廿二號鐵路拓展處處長同埋副處長嚟，我哋嘅言訊咧就引用咗港鐵獨立董事委員會嘅報告，就話港鐵嘅項目團隊向路政署隱瞞咗係隱。
瞞咗項目進度嘅關鍵資訊，嚇，亦即係項目團隊喺二零一三年十一月嘅分析結果係工程完工嘅日期咧，係會延誤去到二零一六年嘅鐵路拓展署更加喺言訊裏邊咧，係清楚指出港鐵隱瞞關鍵資。
資訊而導致到政府咧係做咗呢個叫做工程滯後，不等於最終係延誤呢個錯誤嘅判斷噉樣。所以梁國權先生，你會唔會同意就係港鐵喺項目中進度上邊係有誤導路政署？嚇，你早前嘅陳述書裡。
裏邊第一百三十段咧，就話港鐵從來係從來冇蓄意隱瞞重要嘅資料。你點樣回應路鐵路拓展署呢一個咁嚴重嘅指控？話你哋係項目進度關鍵嘅資訊，你哋係隱瞞咗。你點樣去回應當日嘅言訊裏邊，政府部門？
代表講嘅説話。
I thank you for the question, Honourable Member. Firstly, as I highlighted, there was at all times full disclosure of information to government and the various departments of government. There were regular meetings, significant number of regular meetings, as well as the government's so-called M and V consultant, J.
We're also auditing and doing a significant body of work based on the information. And in addition to the information which we have given, this disclosure of information and following the requirements under the entrustment agreement, I believe are well highlighted in both the IBC and.
The IEP report. Once again, I understand that the statement which Mr. K. K. Lau and Mr. Henry Chang was made was referring to an event back in November of 2013. As I have responded to another honourable member's question on this particular matter.
At that time, the project team was still awaiting. Was still awaiting a programme from the contractors. This was the A Ten A contractor on whether the minimum operating requirement, the so-called MOR, was achievable or not. This request for.
A programme from the contractor of 810A, as I understand it, was also a request from the various members of government. So at that time in November 2013, the event that is being that has been highlighted, the project's team was still awaiting for.
一個program from the contractor to see whether the program, the revised or the program to complete, can be achieved or not.
主席，我問佢嘅問題，問佢嘅責任有冇隱瞞資料，佢而家又將個責任推咗喺承建商嗰度，喺度等嗰啲嘅資訊。主席，我時間剩翻唔多，我想問埋第三個問題，亦都係上一次嘅言訊裏邊講到呢個工程前期工作緊縮嘅誒準準備時間，就導致咗呢個合約編號八一零A八一零。
B同埋八一一A三項涉及到西九龍總站嘅合約咧，係需要做呢個設計修訂。你喺會後裏邊咧，就透過書面係去答我哋本會嗰陣時咧，就話影響同承建商談判作為理由咧，係去拒絕披露呢三份合約裏邊做出嘅修訂次數同。
埋內容而只係引述獨立專家小組報告指出，就八一零A合約去到二零一三年嘅六月，已經係有一萬三千五百一十三次嘅修訂，涉及改正錯別字啊、釐清差異啊、提供額外資料嘅細微修改。我想問梁國權先生，你係用乜？
嘢嘅準則係去定義，係去define呢一萬幾千次嘅修訂，只係細微嘅修改咧。噉樣係，例如如果係以進度影響作為準則，一或係用工程成本係作為準則咧，我嘅質疑，我嘅疑問就係話積少成多，聚沙成塔。呢一萬三千幾個細細微。
嘅更改係咪就係最終係導致咗更加多重大嘅改動，而令到呢個工程延誤，又或者係政府口裏邊講嘅滯後，係變成咗無可挽回。你哋過去做嘅追回進度好多嘅措施，都係唔能夠追回到個進度咧，係一。
一萬三千五百一十三次喎，主席。
梁生。
No, thank you for that question. As highlighted in the IEP report, this is on paragraph 104 of the IEP report. That report does highlight that, as by June 2013, there were 13,513 revised drawings, as also highlighted in the IEP report.
And in our response to a similar question last time, these a number many of these amendments in drawings would be of a minor nature. I would firstly perhaps also say that it is not uncommon for tenders for
要被 tendered once they have reached a certain maturity in design. In the case of 810A, the contract that the honourable member mentioned, that that particular contract had reached a maturity of design that allowed it to be tendered. It is also not uncommon for in these very
Complicated projects for there to be design adjustments. Design adjustments after the contract has been tendered out. The honourable member mentioned the one thirteen five hundred and thirteen drawings were part of these design adjustments. A number of these design adjustments would have been relatively minor in nature. Some of these design adjustments related to
到建設困難，哪個被面臨？例如，地質條件，高亮在第104段的IEP報告，作為一些這些修改圖紙會有附加H柱。附加H柱是因為地質條件困難，特別是他們在一個案例中。
War on the western part of the West Kowloon site. A third cause of the design changes could be changes requested by third parties. So there are a number of causes for these design changes. I would, however, say that many of these design changes when
再次，都係屬於一個非常
were the result of difficulties encountered during construction, and thirdly, some of these design changes were also the result of third-party requests. Thank you, Chairman.
誒，我諗個議員佢問嘅問題就係話，有因為個數量咁多嘅話咧，佢累積起上嚟會唔會係作作會成為一個嚴嘅一個一個好大嘅原因咧？
我會説，在一係數個case，設計變更係屬較小的，其他變更係因為施工困難，施工困難可能造成延誤或變更進度，但係施工。
Construction difficulties then resulted and required different and amended or adjusted design. And thirdly, there could have been design changes from third parties. So it is actually a complicated interaction and interplay of many factors when one looks at these design changes as well as the difficulties encountered.
在Construction。
或者我哋誒，或者我再跟進多一條問題啦。你我哋而家大家都知道啦。
係誒，你嘅前任個個總裁咧。
就係講佢公司前任總裁咧，就係曾經喺誒三年十一月咧，就同局長講我哋翻説話，就係話為咗係佢堅持咧，就唔畀局長向呢個誒。
我哋嘅立法會嘅鐵路小組同埋公眾咧，係開誠佈公，係即係可能會有一個言。咁為咗咧，就係要為向嗰啲誒承建商施加壓力。咁呢個做法咧，即係唔向呢個立法會鐵路小組開誠佈公咧，呢個做法你作為一個。
高層嘅港鐵公司人員咧，係咪認同啊？嗯，Jeremy，Firstly, I would say that at no time was there ever any intention to withhold any information from government or the Legislative Council. Once again, I was not at that meeting when in November twenty.呢個做法，我先問你，我。
知道你當時唔在場，啲事事事先事先，我亦都係即係聽你嘅誒答案咧，亦都係唔知情㗎啦嚇。咁但係即係而家係聽翻轉頭咧，你會唔會認同呢噉嘅做法咧？Chairman，oh，I would my response would be that it is never and will never be MTR's intention to withhold any
信息從政府或立法會。
對。
或者我哋而家係誒有一個誒一個短嘅十十五分鐘嘅誒小休，咁跟住仲有兩位咧係報咗名就係未發問嘅就係李卓人議員同埋鄧家彪議員，唔該啊十五分鐘。